Miriam Davidson Papers, 1979-1989
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Miriam Davidson Papers, 1979-1989
MS 433
Miriam Davidson
Papers, 1979-1989. This collection contains Miriam Davidson's manuscripts and research files for her 1988 book,Convictions of the Heart regarding the 1980's Sanctuary Movement and Trial. Materials include several drafts of the book and Davidson's research materials, the bulk of which include: news clippings, Davidson's trial notes, Sanctuary Movement materials, and cassette tape recordings of Davidson's interviews with various members of the Movement and Trial. The majority of the material is in English, some is in Spanish.
5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions for this collection.
Biographical and Historical Note
Miriam Davidson (b.1960) grew up in the Boston, Massachusetts, area and became a Quaker when she was eleven years old. She graduated from Yale University in 1982 with a B.A. in English and later earned her master's degree in international journalism from the University of Southern California. Davidson has worked as a reporter, editor, journalism professor, freelance writer, and author. In 1982 she moved to Texas and worked as a reporter and Lifestyle editor for the Laredo News and later served as managing editor of Third Coast magazine. Davidson was a University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ, adjunct professor of journalism, 1988-89. From 1993-1996, she worked for the Arizona Republic in Phoenix, Arizona, as a correspondent covering Tucson and Nogales. As a freelance journalist her work has appeared in the New York Times, the Christian Science Monitor, The Nation, the NACLA Report on the Americas, and The Progressive. Davidson's three books include Convictions of the Heart: Jim Corbett and the Sanctuary Movement (1988), Changing Childhood Prejudice: the Caring Work of the Schools written with Florence H. Davidson (1994) and Lives on the Line: Dispatches from the U.S.-Mexico Border with photographs by Jeffry Scott (2000).
The bulk of Davidson's work has been on the U.S.-Mexico border. In 1985, she moved from Texas to Tucson, Arizona, to cover the Sanctuary Movement and subsequent trial. She covered the trial for the Christian Science Monitor and the Religious News Service; her book, Convictions of the Heart was published by the University of Arizona press in 1988. The Sanctuary Movement originated in Tucson, Arizona, during the early 1980s as a means of aid to Central American refugees, especially people fleeing from the political violence in El Salvador and Guatemala. Jim Corbett (1933-2001) along with the Tucson Ecumenical Council, Rev. John Fife (b. 1940), and his congregation declared sanctuary for the refugees. The grass roots movement soon became a national movement with churches all over the United States declaring sanctuary. In 1985, sixteen activists were indicted, eleven - including Corbett and Fife - went to trial and eight were convicted of alien smuggling and other charges. Although the trial ended in 1986, the movement itself has continued and evolved over the past twenty-five years in its original mission to aid refugees.
Organization
This collection is organized into 4 series
Series I: Writings, 1987
Series II: Research Files, 1979-1989
subseries 1: Printed Materials, 1980-1989
subseries 2: Subject Files, 1979-1987
Series III: Audio Materials, 1982-1987
Series IV: Oversize Materials, 1984-1986
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1979-1989. This collection contains Miriam Davidson's manuscripts and research files for her 1988 book, Convictions of the Heart: Jim Corbett and the Sanctuary Movement regarding the early 1980's Sanctuary Movement, which aided Central American political refugees, and the 1985-1986 Trial held in Tucson, Arizona. Materials include several drafts of the book and Davidson's research materials, the bulk of which include: news clippings, Davidson's trial notes, Sanctuary Movement materials, and cassette tape recordings of Davidson's interviews with various members of the Movement and Trial; the bulk of the interviews are with Jim Corbett. The majority of the material is in English, some is in Spanish.
Related Material
Papers of the Sanctuary Movement Trial, 1982-1988 - MS 362
Access Terms
Davidson, Miriam
Corbett, Jim, 1933-2001
Fife, John M. (John Macmillan), 1940-
Sanctuary movement--Arizona--Tucson
Sanctuary movement--United States
Church work with refugees--United States
Political refugees--Central America
Container List
- Writings, 1987
  Arrangement: Chronological. This series contains four drafts of Davidson's book Convictions of the Heart as well as her early book notes.
  - Early Book Notes - Convictions of the Heart. undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Manuscripts - Convictions of the Heart Draft 1. undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Manuscripts - Convictions of the Heart Draft 2. undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Manuscripts - Convictions of the Heart Draft 3. undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts - Convictions of the Heart Draft 4. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Research Files, 1979-1989
  Subseries 1: Printed Materials, 1980-1989 Arrangement: Alphabetical. This subseries contains printed materials such as essays/statements, government documents, magazine and news clippings, as well as newsletters and pamphlets pertaining to the Sanctuary Movement and Trial as well as materials relating to Central America and immigration issues in general. More printed materials, specifically magazines and newspapers, can be found in Series IV: Oversize Materials.
  Subseries 2: Subject Files, 1979-1987 Arrangement: Alphabetical. This subseries contains materials grouped by topic based on Davidson's original organization. Materials include Davidson's notes, news clippings, articles, newsletters, some legal materials, and information packets regarding refugee stories. The bulk of the material is Davison's Trial Notes; she was in court for the duration of the Sanctuary Trial. In most cases, original folder titles have been retained. More subject files materials, specifically regarding John Fife, can be found in Series IV: Oversize Materials.
  - Printed Materials, 1980-1989
    - Essays/Statements. undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Essays/Statements - "The Covenant as Sanctuary" by Jim Corbett. undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Essays/Statements - "Dear Friends." 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Essays/Statements - Defendants' Statement Following Their Arraignment. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Essays/Statements - "Education Strategy" by Tim Nonn to the TEC Task Force for Central America. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Essays/Statements - "Military Operations: What is Legal and What is Illegal" by Karen Parker. 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Essays/Statements - "Obligation of United States to Political Refugees" by Gary MacEoin. undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Essays/Statements - "Pilgrim's update - - - October, '83." 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Essays/Statements - "The Politics of Sanctuary" by Miriam Davidson. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Essays/Statements - "Some Proposals for Integrating Smuggling, Refuge, Relay, Sanctuary, and Bailbond Networks, January-February, '84 (for consideration by the Tucson refugee support groups)." 1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Essays/Statements - Talk in Austin, Oct. 28, 1982. 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Essays/Statements - "Unindicted co-Conspirators: A Position Paper." 1985 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Essays/Statements - "A View from the Border." 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Government Materials - Bill - Central American Studies and Temporary Relief Act. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Government Materials - Briefing Reports - Asylum and Illegal Aliens. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Government Materials - Congressional Records - House. 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Government Materials - Correspondence. undated, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Government Materials - Miscellaneous. undated, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Magazines. 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Magazine Articles and Clippings. undated, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - News Clippings. undated, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - News Cippings. 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Newsletters. undated, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Pamphlets. undated, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Seasonal Missalette - Lent. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Subject Files, 1979-1987
    - Arrest at Naco, Ariz. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Corbett, Jim - Desert - Goats. undated, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Corbett, Jim - International Law and Refugees. undated, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Fife, John - Southside. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Government Informant - Frank Varelli - Dallas FBI. 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous Materials and Notes. undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Nonn, Tim - TEC - Sanc. undated, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Opposition to Sanc. - Carroll, Reno, and the Gov't. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Refugee Stories. undated, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Salvadorans - Organ Pipe National Monument. undated, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Sanctuary Related Burglaries. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Trial - Defendants. undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Trial - Defense and Reno - openings and closings. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Trial - Government Informant - Jesus Cruz. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Trial - Government Informant - John Nixon. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Trial - House Arrest. undated, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Trial - Jury. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Trial - Pre-Trial. undated, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Trial - Trial Notes. undated, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Trial - Trial Notes. 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Trial - Trial Notes. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Trial - Refugee Testimony - Jose Rene Argueta. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Trial - Refugee Testimony - Juana. 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Trial - Refugee Testimony - Rodriguez and Ana B. 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Trial - Verdict. undated, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Audio Materials, 1982-1987
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains the taped interviews conducted by Davidson of various members involved in the Sanctuary Movement and Trial. The majority of the tapes are Davidson's interviews with Jim Corbett. Two tapes include a recording of a service that took place on March 24, 1982 in Southside United Presbyterian Church.
  Although most of the tapes are undated, the interviews took place at some point between 1985-1987. The alphabetical arrangement is based on the interviewee's last name; although two different people may be on the same tape, the arrangement is based on the interview recorded on Tape Side A. Note that the titles listed are based on the overall subject matter discussed during the interview and do not necessarily reflect the tapes' original titles. Also note, the job positions listed were those at the time of the interview or positions of significance during the early 1980's Sanctuary Movement.
  - Tape 1 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement. 1986 (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Tape 2 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement & May 4, 1981 Events. 1986 (Box 3, Item 2)
  - Tape 3 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement & Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services. undated (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Tape 4 Side A Jim Corbett El Centro Detention Center - Regarding the May 30, 1981 Events &Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: May 1986. Side B Lupe Castillo, paralegal for the Manzo Area Council Manzo Area Council and Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: June/July 1986. 1986 (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Tape 5 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Visits to Central America Interview date: August 1986. 1986 (Box 3, Item 5)
  - Tape 6 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Side A Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Side B Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services &Thoughts on the Trial Interview date: Summer 1986. 1986 (Box 3, Item 6)
  - Tape 7 Sides A and B Jim Corbett Side A Sanctuary Movement - various topics Side B Thoughts on the Trial. undated (Box 3, Item 7)
  - Tape 8 Side A Jim Corbett Thoughts on US-Central America Side B Blank. 1987 (Box 3, Item 8)
  - Tape 9 Sides A and B Jim Dudley, Quaker - friend of Corbett and Shutts & high-school math teacher from Albuquerque Regarding the May 4,1981 Events, Quaker Organizations, & Immigration Experiences Interview date: August 1, 1985 Last Third of Side B Jim Corbett Topics: Jesus Cruz and Judge Carroll Interview date: undated. undated, 1985 (Box 3, Item 9)
  - Tape 10 Sides A and B John Fife, pastor of Southside United Presbyterian Church Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement & Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services. undated (Box 3, Item 10)
  - Tape 11 Sides A and B John Fife, pastor of Southside United Presbyterian Church Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement, Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services, Thoughts on US-Central America Policy & Thoughts on the Trial Interview date: February 3, 1987 Second Half of Side B Jim Corbett Sanctuary Movement - various topics Interview date: undated. undated, 1987 (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Tape 12 Sides A and B Marianne Fife, John Fife's wife and sanctuary worker Life Pre-Sanctuary Movement, Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services, & Thoughts on the Trial. undated (Box 3, Item 12)
  - Tape 13 Sides A and B Robert Hirsh, defense attorney for John Fife Thoughts on the Trial Interview Date: 1987. 1987 (Box 3, Item 13)
  - Tape 14 Sides A and B Ken Kennon, pastor of Broadway Christian Church and Tucson Ecumenical Council (TEC) Task Force on Central America member TEC and Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: June/July 1986 Second Half of Side B March 24, 1982 Southside Church Service Last Third of Tape is Blank. 1982,1986 (Box 3, Item 14)
  - Tape 15 Side A Barry Lazarus, Tucson jeweler - friend of Corbett Regarding the "Naco Five" Incident on February 2, 1986 in Naco, Az Interview date: November 1986 Side B Jim Corbett Sanctuary Movement - various topics Interview date: undated. undated,1986 (Box 3, Item 15)
  - Tape 16 Side A Tim Nonn, seminary student at St. Mark's and TEC Task Force on Central America project director 1981-1982 TEC and Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: August 26, 1985 Last Third of the Tape is Blank Side B Gary MacEoin, journalist, lawyer, and author Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: undated. undated,1985 (Box 3, Item 16)
  - Tape 17 Side A March 24, 1982 Southside Church Service Side B Dave Sholin, chief pastor at St. Mark’s Presbyterian Church and TEC member TEC and Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Interview date: undated. undated,1982 (Box 3, Item 17)
  - Tape 18 Sides A and B Frank Shutts, member of the Claremont, California, Friends Meeting Regarding the May 4, 1981 Events Interview Date: July/August 1985 Side B: Bill Johnston, Director of the Tucson INS Regarding the June 26, 1981 Events, INS Policy, & Thoughts on the Sanctuary Movement Interview Date: June 1986. 1985-1986 (Box 3, Item 18)
  - Tape 19 Sides A and B Mike Smith, assistant pastor at St. Mark's and president of the TEC in 1981 and appointed chairman of the TEC Task Force on CA TEC and Sanctuary Movement Activities and Services Note: Side B is Mostly Blank. undated (Box 3, Item 19)
- Oversize Materials, 1984-1987
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains materials pertaining to Davidson's Research Files; contents include oversize magazines and newspapers.
  - Research Files; Printed Materials: Magazines. 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Research Files; Printed Materials: Newspapers. 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Research Files; Subject Files: Fife, John - Southside. 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)